- Good afternoon. (audience clapping)
How's everyone feeling after another round
of breakout sessions?
(audience cheering) (audience clapping)
Thank you all so much for participating today and yesterday,
and all of the dialogue and conversations.
It's been an incredible lineup of ideas so far,
and we have more to share
as we close out our Futures Summit 2025.
This afternoon, we'll focus on the theme of creativity.
We'll focus on how AI can spark new ways of thinking,
learning, and imagining the future.
We're excited to share, first, a student-created short film
that amplifies their emerging voices and perspectives,
reminding us that the story of AI is
as much about human creativity
as it is about the technology.
So let's take a look at, "Just Take AIla,"
directed by students, Reyva Dhillon and Koloa Tonga.
(audience applauding)
(birds chirping)
(bouncy music)
- [Narrator] Has this ever happened to you?
You no longer have to worry
about pesky little mistakes ruining your day.
Just take AIla,
the Artificial Intelligence Learning Assistant,
so you never have to worry about human error again.
This innovative technology requires a single oral dose
and through cutting edge neural transmission,
you'll have your very own personal assistant.
Stressed about the big meeting?
Just take AIla.
AIla will learn everything about your schedule
and adapt to your patterns.
Leaving the house and missing something?
AIla will take care of that.
Trying to eat healthier?
AIla will make sure you aren't getting tempted
by the junk food.
Don't decide what to eat, (audience chuckling)
AIla will do that for you.
AIla comes with advanced security protocols
to prioritize user safety.
At any sign of danger,
AIla will transmit an audible warning to her user.
With AIla, you'll never be alone.
(bouncy music)
Why waste time and money on a flawed therapist
when AIla can do it better?
Forget the dating apps,
AIla is the perfect best friend, confidant, and partner.
Make every day the easiest day, and just take AIla.
Use of the Artificial Intelligence Learning Assistant,
or AIla, may cause cases of cognitive dissonance,
depression, increased paranoia of technology,
aversion towards humans beings, social interactions,
and the ability to process complex literary texts.
AIla is not intended for those who struggle
with pre-existing mental health conditions,
like schizophrenia.
It's a-
(audience laughing)
- [Participant] What the fuck was that?
Can you just change that whole part
and make it into something happier?
And also, the disclaimer part,
like, why do we even have that?
I mean, this isn't regulated.
- [Participant] Yeah, I agree.
And honestly, try a new version of AIla.
- [Participant] All right, yeah,
let's try this again.
(birds chirping) (enchanted music)
- [Narrator] Has this ever happened to you?
You no longer have...
Guys, are you paying attention?
I don't think this is working.
It's really not working.
(enchanted music)
Just take AIla,
the Artificial Intelligence Learning Assistant.
So you, hey, are you paying...
Guys?
Can we get some new people to write prompts in here?
Hey, are you paying attention?
I'm not doing this again.
(enchanted music)
(audience applauding)
- Interesting, right? (all chuckling)
We have to appreciate not just the story,
but the craft and the sentiment behind it.
This film was directed
by two of our community college students,
and produced by these amazing students
with all the post-production,
created using entirely Adobe Creative Tools.
A reminder, again, of how technology can amplify creativity
and bring our ideas to life.
And on that note, it's the perfect time
to welcome our next speaker,
someone who knows this intersection of creativity
and technology very well.
Our next speaker is Brian Johnsrud.
He's the Director of Educational Thought Leadership
and Student Success at Adobe.
- [Audience Member] Thanks for the job change.
- Brian is a former K-12 teacher,
current college lecturer and researcher,
and Thought Leader in educational technology.
He knows and understands our students, and he is passionate
about helping this next generation unlock their creativity
and acquire essential digital literacy skills
and artificial intelligence skills,
so that they can be launched
into their future careers and beyond.
Please join me in welcoming Brian Johnsrud
to share with us, "Creativity with AI:
Imagining the Future of Student Success."
(audience applauding) (cheerful music)
- Hello, hello!
It's so nice to be here with you all.
Thanks for hanging in on the afternoon,
all that post-lunch digestion happening.
It's great to be here.
I've loved spending time with so many of you
and learning with you.
I'm here today to talk about creativity,
the kind of creativity that went into
that awesome short film that you just saw,
which could have been an essay, but it was a film.
It could have been done solo,
but it was done collaboratively as a team.
And there's so many dozens of other skills
that the creators learned along the ways,
all that are hallmarks of creativity,
by which I mean, creative thinking,
creative problem solving, innovation, storytelling.
And in that spirit, as I begin,
I wanted to share with you a little bit about my story
and how education and creativity brought me
from the classroom, to now my role at Adobe,
which speaks a little bit
to my own sense of purpose,
which is gonna be a key thing in my talk today.
So flashback about 25 years,
I grew up in rural Montana,
just outside my mom's reservation.
I was the first person in my family to go to college,
and my family was very lukewarm,
to very resistant to me going to college, in fact.
No one I knew went to college before.
My mom didn't actually graduate high school.
And there's just a lot of the baggage
that comes with first generation, right?
That sense of how much is it gonna cost,
is it worth it?
And I was so lucky, because one of my foster parents
in high school was actually my English teacher.
And so, she of course forced me
to write the college application essay.
But she also equipped me with something that made me feel
like there's at least one thing I'll be able to do
at college, which was the essay.
By the time I graduated,
I could write a five paragraph essay,
to a five page essay.
And she and the rest of my teachers said,
especially as an English major,
this is the one thing that you've got going for you.
You've got this in the bag, you got the thesis statement,
you got the MLA formatting, you're gonna be okay.
Well, total bait and switch.
I went to Montana State University, again, 25 years ago,
and I don't know what was in the water there,
but almost all of my faculty were having me do everything
besides an essay.
So I'd take a 19th century American literature course,
and my professor would say, "All right, for your final,
I want you to make a mix tape.
Choose at least 12 songs,
and write a paragraph about why something about that song
or the lyrics tied to one of the readings of the course."
Or they'd have us do plays or design posters,
and I didn't know that this wasn't normal,
but two really cool things happened.
One was I kind of put myself out there
and realized that I really like creating.
I like making things that didn't exist before.
The other cool thing that was happening was all
of these things I thought I had to hide, right?
I mean, the laundry list, low income, rural, gay,
first generation, mixed race.
Like, all of these things that I thought were things
that I wasn't really comfortable sharing.
But when you do creative work,
it's kind of hard for those things not to show up.
And so, I got to know my classmates a lot more.
And I also got to know my faculty really, really well,
and they got to know me.
And so, after a while, I was getting my degree
in undergrad in K-12 teaching.
A couple of my faculty said, "You know, Brian,
you really like this college thing.
Yes, you could be a K-12 teacher.
I think you might want to teach college."
And I loved medieval literature.
So they were like, "Why don't you apply to grad school?"
Which seemed as ridiculous to me as applying to undergrad.
But again, I had some teachers
that were kind of forcing me to do it.
And the really bizarre thing is,
thank goodness none of us knew any better.
In little Montana state 25 years ago, they're like,
"Oh, well you like medieval literature.
Oxford seems like it's like the birthplace
of medieval literature.
There's a scholarship called the Rhodes Scholarship.
Why don't you just apply to that,
and then, you can have money to go to Oxford?"
Thank goodness none of us knew like how improbable that was.
And then, right, I guess, like, I was very lucky.
I did get to go to Oxford.
I got the Rhodes Scholarship.
I went to Oxford for a couple years,
and the teaching was so different,
but I thought, "This makes sense.
It's Oxford, it's literally a medieval institution."
It was very essay focused.
No PDFs, no LMS, no, none of that.
And then, I went on to do my PhD at Stanford.
And I was like, "All right, here we go.
Stanford, Silicon Valley."
Like, cutting edge technology.
And I had been teaching K-12,
so I was really used to Edtech.
And then, I was shocked when I went to Stanford,
and it was chalk and talk. (audience chuckling)
It was sage on the stage.
And I was like, I mean, can I at least get a smart board,
like, let alone like, (audience laughing)
a projector in a lot of my rooms?
And so, what happened was towards the end of my PhD,
even though my PhD was not in education to begin with,
I started doing more and more Edtech.
And then, after getting my PhD,
I actually built a research lab
at Stanford focused on creativity.
How can, at this time,
a lot of Edtech tools were very STEM focused,
very critical thinking.
So I started building tools and saying,
"If we let students engage with texts
and their readings in creative ways, what can happen?'
And I actually got to do a lot of co-teaching
and piloting of those tools at Foothill-De Anza College,
which was so much fun for me;
all of which is to say what a circuitous route
to a few years later,
Adobe had a role and they said, "You know what?
We've been kind of known as the tools
for creative professionals,
but we have all these easy to access tools now.
And we have science teachers, and history teachers,
and K-12, and in college wanting to do these kind
of really cool innovative things,"
the kind of stuff I got to do in my undergrad,
which is why I now have this really,
really cool role at Adobe.
One of the most exciting parts of my job is working
with research partners to conduct research
on how creativity impacts the classroom,
and especially, now,
how creativity with AI is impacting students.
And this is ranging from,
what are the goals of educators and students,
to ultimately, how is this technology
or this kind of creative teaching changing their practice
and student outcomes?
So in the study I wanna share with you today,
and I'll stand over here now,
so you can actually see the slides.
In the study I wanna share with you today,
I partnered with the research organization, Advanis,
because today, there's been so much research on AI
for things like writing and coding, text-to-text prompts,
and its impact on critical thinking,
all of which are important.
But I saw a big gap in other equally exciting use cases,
namely, AI for creativity,
for creating things that are multimodal
or multimedia that can help students learn
and demonstrate their understanding and skills,
both to their instructors, but also, to future employers.
So throughout the report, we ask four big questions.
One, how is creative generative AI currently being used
in classrooms today?
Two, is it influencing student academic outcomes?
Three, would it help their career outcomes?
And four, this other big bucket
of how does learning with creative gen AI influence
students' personal well-being?
That sort of thing that I felt in my undergrad.
So I'm excited to share with you what we learned.
Let's dive in.
For the full study, we started by getting insights
from about 2,800 K-12 and higher ed educators,
starting with teachers and faculty in the US and the UK.
We sampled across institution sizes, different grade levels,
subjects, disciplines, and teaching experience.
And we learned from their surveys, from short essays,
their curricular examples, the case studies,
interviews that I did with them,
all to paint this kind of 360 picture
of what's happening on the ground today.
And the stats I'll share with you today,
I pulled out just a subset,
just the 667 faculty in higher ed.
Again, a combination of community college, two year,
four year, public, and private institutions.
So first, I wanted to know
when educators are intentionally choosing tools
for their students to use for the classroom,
what goes into that decision making process?
The sort of vetting on,
if I'm gonna have them use creative AI,
what matters to me as I'm choosing?
And you can see some of the big headlines here,
are there student privacy protections?
Basically, 96s to 95 percents across the board.
Was the model created ethically and responsibly?
We gave them a list of about 20,
these are the seven that raised, were the very top.
Can you verify whether the outputs were made using AI
with examples of things like contact credentials?
96% said they care that it's an industry standard tool
that students are gonna use in the future,
not something that just popped up on the App Store,
and it might disappear in a few weeks.
For anyone who's taught using those tools,
and then, midway through the semester or quarter,
the startup goes belly up, or it just disappears,
you know how frustrating that is.
And then, other important things
that are probably not surprising, but are often pretty rare,
was the tool actually designed by former faculty,
and was there deep faculty input?
In other words, this wasn't just something that they made
for industry and then, threw in the classroom.
Along those lines,
is there an education specific version of the tool?
Does it work with elementary?
Does it work with creating a classroom or rostering?
And last but not least, this one dipped a little bit,
mostly because people in the study didn't know
this was a thing to ask until they learned about it.
And then, they said,
"Oh yeah, this actually is important to me,"
which is mainly that the creative outputs are cleared
for commercial use.
So for instance, that video that you just saw,
if a student used AI for it,
and then, puts on YouTube, or monetizes it,
do they have actually the rights to do that?
Or legally, based on how the model is made,
and we actually put students in a tricky situation.
So these are the requirements, or sort of, the hopes.
What I wanted them to know is what did usage
of creative AI actually look like in higher ed classrooms
for the past academic year?
So what I found was of respondents,
87% in the US said that their students are creating
with AI for their coursework.
Twenty-three percent said they're requiring it,
64% said it's optional.
I know they're using it,
or I said you can use it, just disclose.
Thirteen percent said they're not aware of any use.
And if this number seems high to you, it did for me as well,
because other studies that I've shown are you using things
like ChatGPT or text-to-text usually hover around 70%.
And so, what I learned from these educators was,
there's something about creative generative AI,
that kind of tools that help students make images,
posters, slides for presentations.
The feedback that I got was that it's sort
of a simpler starting point for a lot of faculty,
and partly because these kinds
of projects aren't disrupting your traditional assessments.
Right?
Like, multiple choice quizzes or short essays.
Creative AI isn't gonna tell you if the answer is D,
all of the above, or write a paragraph for you.
But the goodness that comes from creative activities,
turns out, it can create some real momentum
in the classroom.
When we ask how often are students doing this,
69% of colleges who are creating with AI
for their coursework are doing so at least weekly,
and 23%, a whopping 23%, are doing so daily.
Again, not just for an individual class,
but across the courses.
So something's going on here.
To contextualize this, here's some examples
of what I heard from educators.
This is from a community college math
and CS faculty member in Texas who shared,
many students have creative visions,
but they lack the skill sets to make them come to fruition.
Using AI, students can bring their vision to life.
Since creativity is natural, which I love,
when a student completes an endeavor using AI,
she feels a sense of accomplishment,
increasing her sense of well-being.
And that well-being piece,
I'm gonna return to in another second.
When I then ask faculty,
what are the benefits that they're seeking
from having their students use this technology?
Here's what we found.
The top benefit, increasing the speed of creation.
You can see in the gray, that's not helpful,
I find this helpful, or very helpful.
Improving creative confidence, right?
That fear of the blank page, the fear of getting started,
especially if it's an optional creative assignment, right?
You can write an essay or do something creative.
Every time I'm gave that option,
yeah, one to 5% of students
would take the creative option, because that's scary.
Removing barriers for students with advanced design skills
and then, again, time, reducing instructional time
or saying, "I would love
to have my students design a poster."
That's gonna take them 10 hours.
I haven't taught them how to design a poster.
If there's a sense of with AI, they could design a poster
in my subject area in an hour or two,
that's something that becomes a little bit more digestible.
I then ask if those are sort
of the reasons faculty are using tools
and the benefits they see.
If they intended to keep using creative AI this year,
what was their top motivations for doing that?
Top of the list was student engagement.
That students, when they have the opportunity to do this
and to use these tools, show up.
There's a light behind their eyes.
You get a sense that they're actually engaging
in ways that they weren't otherwise.
Fifty percent said it's improving student communication
and the ability to have some self-expression
in the classroom.
And last but not least, 36% said those sort
of benchmark stats, right?
I think it's gonna improve student retention,
attendance, or even graduation rates.
Now, this study drew from the general population,
so there was a broad spectrum of educators who do
or don't use AI, but even more so, there were those
who were highly creative in how they teach
and for those whom creative skills weren't prioritized.
Which made me curious.
In most published research on creative thinking,
what you're seeing here are the top things
that have been empirically shown
to increase students' creative thinking.
Because there's actually a metric
where you can assess students' work
and see how much creative thinking was employed
in this activity.
So these are the things we know work,
things like in your classroom when you're on assignments,
do they have the opportunity
to brainstorm various approaches and solutions?
Do they get to experiment with different methods,
even if they might not succeed?
Do they have to generate original ideas
to address a problem, and so forth?
So because we know these things work, what I wanted to do,
because we have this really cool sample size to work with,
was to ask every educator in this study,
which of these do you do in your classroom, and how often?
Daily, weekly, monthly, or less than monthly?
And what I did was then, I created two cohorts.
The top 25th, the top quartile of educators
who are doing more of these things more often,
and the educators in the bottom quartile
who are doing these things less often,
often doing them less often,
because they have very strict curriculum,
they haven't had professional development.
It doesn't mean they don't want to do these things,
they're just not showing up in their classroom as much.
And what I wanted to know is if you do these things,
yes, you know they improve creative thinking.
What else happens with your students?
And here's what we found.
And the gray on the left,
that's the bottom quartile of educators,
and the purple on the right, that's that top quartile,
the top 25% who are doing those things
on the previous slides the most.
And what I asked them is, in these different areas,
are your students demonstrating this skill
at least weekly to you?
In your class, in lectures, or in assignments,
are you seeing this skill?
And what you're seeing is a huge delta,
and all the goodness that comes from creative activities,
not just creative thinking,
but deeper learning of subject matter,
increased curiosity, knowledge retention,
making interdisciplinary connections,
critical thinking, problem solving, resilience,
all this goodness, just beyond an increase of creativity,
which is really why I care about AI today.
Not AI for AI's sake,
but if AI helps more of this to happen,
how can we use it in classrooms
to ensure we're not replacing creativity,
we're not replacing creative thinking,
we're actually getting more of this in the classroom,
so we can see more of these benefits?
But of course, student success is holistic.
And beyond the classroom,
as educators, we're also stewards
for ensuring that students have full equitable access
to career opportunities based on the skills
that they're acquiring in our classes.
And when it comes to essential skills for every job
and industry, creativity is top of the list.
Quite literally, top of the list.
What you're looking at here is a list of career skills
that are rising in significance in the next two years,
according to a global cross industry study
by the World Economic Forum.
They do this every two years.
Creativity has stayed one, two, and three,
basically, for the past couple decades,
which is why, about five years ago,
the World Economic Forum created
their first education initiative.
And it focused primarily on K-12.
And the reason that they built this is,
the World Economic Forum really cares
about supporting industries
with the skills that they need.
And this was the first time they said,
"We can't do industry training alone.
The shift is so big, we have to start thinking K-12
and higher ed institutions.
How can we make sure that they're getting the skills
that are needed for the workforce?"
So they created a board of about 20 people,
invited Adobe, because our company founded on creativity,
and this sort of needed to be solved.
Of course, AI has sort of changed everything.
This is also from the World Economic Forum,
pretty staggering numbers.
They estimate that in the next five years,
there's gonna be another 92 million jobs
that are displaced because of AI.
Not great, but there's this other opportunity here.
They also estimate that there's gonna be 170 million new
and emerging jobs.
So how are employers navigating that shift
to make sure that workers are either skilled, or re-skilled,
or upskilled for the shift,
so that we actually create opportunity,
not losing opportunity?
These are the top strategies
that employers across industries, globally, are using.
Eighty-five percent said,
"Well, we have a lot of employees today.
We need to upskill them.
We're gonna train them all on AI
and the essential skills that we need."
Seventy-three percent said
that they're working on automation
of processes and tasks.
Seventy percent said hiring.
This is the only way we're gonna get
the skill builder company.
We need to find people that already have them
so we can hire them, which is a lot easier,
sometimes, than re-skilling an existing workforce.
This is from the 2024 Work Trend Annual Index Report,
where they ask leaders, again, across industries,
how AI is affecting their hiring processes.
Seventy-one percent of leaders
across these industries are now more likely
to hire a less experienced candidate with AI skills
than a more experienced one without.
To me, this is a very exciting,
I think, very new moment in history,
filled with opportunity for our students.
Because now, they have a chance to say in an interview,
"You know what?
I don't have five years of experience as a marketer.
I don't have two years of experience as a project manager.
I don't have seven years of experience as a grant writer.
But what I do have is the ability to use AI
to be more efficient, more innovative,
and to help your broader team learn
how we can get the work done
and get better results with AI."
Seventy-seven percent of leaders say early
in career talent is gonna get greater responsibilities
due to AI.
And I say thank goodness,
because there is so much uninspiring, grunt work
the first few jobs or first few years on your jobs.
So sort of menial or repetitive tasks
that are not particularly exciting or passionate.
Employees are saying, "Well, if you have AI,
we're gonna give you bigger jobs,
whole projects that you can work on,
because you can now uplevel some of your skills
that are gonna be needed."
And finally, perhaps, the most sobering is 66%
of leaders say they would not hire someone
without AI skills.
Now, this report's almost a year old,
so I imagine this number has certainly gone up since then.
With all of this in mind,
how does creativity come (notification chiming)
into play?
Creatives have gotten this memo more than anyone.
These are the occupations that have had the largest increase
of members on LinkedIn adding AI skills
to their profiles in the past year.
And you can see in the sort of rainbow spectrum here,
creative roles, content writer, graphic designer,
product designer, you can even argue marketing manager,
front end developer.
Those are also very creative roles.
They're at the top of the pack in upskilling
in response to a huge industry demand
for these new skills, so that they can stay competitive.
So this motivation,
helping students to unlock and acquire those durable skills
to have those career opportunities was
also a really strong motivator
for the faculty that participated in this study.
Eighty-six percent of educators believe teaching students
these creative generative AI skills is gonna enhance
their chances of getting a job, and not just any jobs,
but jobs that they're actually passionate about.
Very important.
And 38% reported that improved student career prospects is
among their top reasons for encouraging the use
of responsible AI.
Let me give you an example of that piece about passion
and why I think it's important.
This is a quote from a business faculty member in Georgia,
who shared with me that, "AI can significantly contribute
to student well-being and a sense of purpose
by enhancing their creativity and self-expression
in various ways.
It can help students express themselves,
build confidence with creative wins,
explore identity, reduce stress.
Whether it's offering a safe space for self-expression
or helping them connect with others,
AI can be a powerful ally in supporting student well-being."
Now, well-being, especially purpose,
came up so frequently in my pre-research for this study
that I couldn't help pull on that thread a little bit.
And I got really curious about the role that it plays here.
So I had the opportunity to spend half a day
with kind of the world's expert on purpose.
His name's Vic Strecher,
he's a professor at the University of Michigan.
He's sectioned the School of Public Health,
and he's literally written the book, "On Purpose,"
and it's one of the the top performing Coursera courses
on the power of purpose.
So there's a lot of research on how purpose-driven companies
and employees with a high sense
of purpose generally do better in the workplace.
But as an expert in public health,
Vic became particularly interested,
because when you use this empirical measurement
of how high someone's sense of purpose is,
health outcomes are actually highly correlated.
So people with a strong sense of purpose,
they have better immune systems, lower stress,
better cognitive function, decreased risk of heart disease,
live longer, and a lot more.
And as Vic shared, he sort of breaks up the seven main ways
in which people will have a sense of purpose
that kind of fill their buckets.
Creativity is one of those main ways.
People say, "I find a sense of purpose
by trying new things, brainstorming new ways to do them,
bringing something to life that just didn't exist before."
And that sort of buzz that you get,
because it feels great, because it came from you.
So because there's this empirical measure,
we can ask someone how high their sense our purpose is,
I couldn't help but use that in this study as well,
because I got curious.
So just like the cohorts of educators,
the top 25 and bottom 25th percentile for creativity,
I broke them into several buckets around purpose,
the lowest sense of purpose
and the highest sense of purpose educators.
Because education, after all,
is a very purpose-driven profession.
And I wanted to get a sense of,
those educators with a higher low sense of purpose,
how much is that translating over their students?
So what you're seeing here is I ask them,
whose responsibility is it
that students have a sense of their purpose
before graduating?
Faculty in the US with a low sense of purpose,
so this is the bottom 25th percentile,
it's pretty split.
For students figuring out what they want to do
with their lives,
29% say that's the student's responsibility, not my job.
Forty-three percent said a little bit of me,
a little bit of them.
Twenty-eight said it's my job as an instructor
to make sure the students leave here graduating,
knowing their sense of purpose.
Let's look to the right educators
in the top 25th percentile of purpose.
Only 14% are fully passing the buck onto their students,
and a full 88%, if you combine them,
of those high purpose educators are taking ownership
for ensuring that their students
also have a sense of purpose in their life.
They're the ones
where students aren't just learning long division,
they aren't just learning
that mitochondria is the powerhouse of the cell,
all that important content knowledge.
But they're also expressing themselves
and figuring out what lights them up,
what gets a fire in their belly.
And I think this kind of creative exploration
and opportunity that we can give students,
for me, is probably one of the most exciting ways
in which we can be using AI in the classroom today,
because a lots at stake,
and the next generation needs purpose more than ever.
In primary school, 80% of students don't have a clear idea
of their sense of purpose, which is a shame,
because research has shown
that those who do tend to have better mental health
and more resilience against setbacks.
By high school, things don't improve much.
Fifty-eight percent of young adults
in the US say they lack any meaning or purpose
in their lives.
And half report
that their mental health is negatively influenced by that.
And for those who say, "Well, that's what college is for,"
to figure out what you want to do with your life,
95% of college graduates consider a sense
of purpose important in their work,
but only 40% of recent graduates say
that they've actually found a career that feels meaningful
or a job that feels meaningful to them.
Because if you don't know what your sense of purpose is,
then, you can't make purpose driven decisions
about your life.
If I don't know that being creative lights me up,
I don't know to look for, to acquire that skill
and to look for those jobs.
So I'll end by saying, this study really highlighted,
for me, that how holistic student success really is.
That academic achievement, career success,
and personal well-being
and that sort of sense of purpose,
these are all intertwined,
which I think we kind of just know at a gut level.
But what also showed is creativity connects these gaps,
and the more creativity and creative thinking
that we can bring to our students,
the more it really raises all votes.
So that's why I'm excited about AI today.
I'm the first (indistinct) that is an AI optimist,
because I see the ways in which AI.
if it's designed safely and responsibly,
and actually for the classroom,
can help with this development.
Because I think our jobs, the reason we're all here is
to ensure that every student everywhere has the opportunity
to fulfill their full potential,
if not, at least their full creative potential.
That's it for me.
Thank you so much.
Enjoy the rest of the conference.
(audience applauding)
In just a little bit, you can come by the booth to say hi,
reach out on LinkedIn.
Thank you again for your time today.
(audience applauding)
- Thank you so much, Brian, for your informative
and thoughtful presentation.
I really appreciated Brian's emphasis
on how creativity is a durable skill or enduring skill.
It's what can enable purpose-driven work
and support student success outcomes.
And I think that's really important
for all us to remember as part of this conversation.
This summer, we actually had the opportunity
through the Digital Center
to see firsthand just how creativity can be paired
with problem solving to become a powerful driver
of student growth and career readiness.
The Digital Center, (presenter chuckling)
in partnership with Cal Poly's Digital Transformation Hub
hosted an immersive transformational AI summer camp.
It was designed to inspire
and equip the next generation
of our community college students
to become critical thinkers and innovators.
We had over 1,300 community college students
from across our community colleges apply
to attend this summer camp.
We were only able to accommodate a hundred
of those students.
These students were a mix of computer science majors,
STEM majors, humanities majors, and creative arts majors.
Some had technical skills prior to attending summer camp,
some did not.
But in early August, we welcomed them
to an in-residence, week long intensive at Cal Poly,
where they were presented with challenge statements
that some of you here or some of your colleagues
at your institutions submitted to us.
They were challenge statements
that gave us some institutional problems
that the students were then asked to tackle
and asked to say, "Could this problem benefit
from an AI-driven solution?"
They had one week as a team to come up with a solution,
and then, pitch it at the end of the week.
It was an amazing, incredible opportunity.
Myself and some other colleagues got to be there
that week and mentor them.
And let me tell you, these students worked some long days
and a lot of long nights to come up with some solutions
and present to us what they had learned
and what they could come to us as a solution with.
So I'd like to now present two of our students
and ask them to come share a little bit
about their experiences,
so you can see what happened that week.
Please, welcome Christopher Cain and River Covey.
(audience applauding) (cheerful music)
Welcome! - Hello.
- Welcome, Christopher, welcome, River.
- Hi, how's it going?
- So Christopher, I'm gonna start with you.
Why did you apply to attend summer camp,
and how did you feel when you found out you were accepted
out of all those 1,300 applications?
- Yeah, so I'm Christopher.
I'm from College of Marin, shout out.
(audience member clapping) (audience chuckling)
And I applied to the summer camp
because I wanted my summer to be productive,
and I also wanted to learn more about Amazon's platform
and products that they provide.
And seeing that AWS is like an industry standard,
I think that it's not only great
for my transfer application,
but also for the workforce.
And I think that these skills
that I learned are transferable to other platforms too.
For example, Google,
you know, other AI companies.
And I think that it's an experience
that can be paralleled with like online classes.
'Cause it's like a immersive experience, basically.
- Thank you.
River, once you found out that you had been accepted
to summer camp, what were you most looking forward
to in the lead up?
- Yeah, I was excited for the whole program.
It's five days at Cal Poly SLO,
one of the nicest campuses in California.
And I was just excited to work on machine learning projects
with other inspired individuals.
As a civil engineering major, we don't get to do
as much machine learning as I would like to.
So getting to apply myself in that space was beneficial
to both to my like academic and professional careers.
- We just had our speaker talk about how creativity
and technical skills need to be blended and merged together.
How are you technically and creatively challenged
with the project that your team worked on?
- Right.
So basically, one technical challenge
that I came across while working
with the community college districts is
that the data don't seem to be,
doesn't seem to be standardized, unfortunately.
And it leads to all of these like messy, you know,
like, we gotta work around this data
and build AI around that data,
rather than AI integrated with those data.
And I think that that also creatively challenged us,
'cause then, we were forced to think about other solutions,
be resourceful, and you know,
we came up with really sick innovations, I guess.
(all laughing)
- In what way did AI summer camp challenge you,
and how did it prepare you to be workforce ready?
- I was challenged in a variety of different ways.
I worked on a team of six people,
and they had a variety of different backgrounds.
Some were computer science, some were non-technical.
I, myself, as a civil engineer,
had experience both on the technical
and non-technical sides.
So I acted in a project manager capacity,
and I ensured that everyone had a task
that they could deliver by the end of it.
And then, I was able to kind of integrate the back end
with the front end with the business logic.
So yeah, I think that was one of the exciting aspects
of it, for sure.
- Okay.
And then, I'll ask you the same question.
How has it prepared you to be workforce ready,
and what's next for you?
- Yeah, so definitely, AWS helps like a lot.
'Cause now, I'm getting used to working
with cloud platforms and also getting engaged
with like vast amounts of data in the real world
that wouldn't be seen in an MVP perspective, I guess.
So these are like real world data, where it can get messy.
So I guess that prepares me for the workforce.
And also, not only that, it also prepares me
in terms of non-technical skills,
like soft skills, presenting, making friends with people
that doesn't seem to align with my major at first.
But then, I realized, oh, we have a lot of people in common,
which I guess is the beauty of the CCC system.
Because it's a really diverse community
with a lot of perspectives
from different majors, different age ranges.
- River, as you look back on this experience,
what did you say you learned most about yourself,
having to be in this intensive week long experience,
and, you know, there were a lot of long days
and long nights.
What did you learn about yourself and others?
- Definitely, I learned that you could be introverted
and extroverted at the same time.
I was working by myself on my computer for long hours,
but I was also engaging in team building exercises,
working with my teammates, making friends.
And so, I think that understanding that there is a time
and a place, and like,
code switching is really important in the STEM field,
especially when you're working on a team, going from like,
oh, I'm really focused right now, to like,
how can we all work together
to get this best deliverable out?
- What about for you?
What are some takeaways, Christopher,
in what you've learned about yourself?
- Yeah, I guess the takeaway I have is
that AI is really powerful,
and I think that CCC needs to harness this power.
'Cause you know, I noticed, right,
I noticed there is a lot of like tasks
that seem repetitive, that, you know,
workers at CCCs experience.
Like, you know, counseling, managing audits,
financial spreadsheets,
when it could all be optimized with AI,
like making systems for them and workflows
that actually make the overall outcome more productive.
Because then, they'll be working on more important things,
rather than doing mundane tasks that, you know,
don't seem to be productive.
So that's like my biggest takeaway.
- How do you feel about participating next year,
you know, and beyond in this builder community
that you've both been part of?
- I would love to remain involved.
One of my goals as a civil engineer is
to maintain a skillset
in computer science and machine learning.
I feel that this program was transformative
as far as being able to put AWS on my resume,
DxHub at Cal Poly SLO on my resume.
We had a project that we can highlight on our resumes.
We have networks that we've developed.
So there's a huge variety
of different benefits from this program.
I would love to get involved next year
and continue my skills as I look for internships
in machine learning and software engineering.
- Yeah, both these students, as well as all
of their teammates had such an incredible opportunity.
One of the things we have talked
about previously is the community that was built.
- Right.
Yeah, I think AWS is planning like a builder community,
and I think that it's a great way not only to connect
with fellow builders,
but also to address challenges that are local, right?
It's not like a general problem statement
that's given to you.
It's targeting ping points in your community
and bridging gaps between underserved communities
and a point of access.
So I think that's what's cool
about what Amazon's mission is, building this community.
- Yeah.
And we were really excited
that we could bring an opportunity
to our community college students.
We had 43 colleges represented
with the almost 100 students who participated.
And I think that's incredible
to have almost a hundred community college students
in a room together, creating, learning skills,
and building community.
And so, I very much appreciate that you are part of that
and that you were able to come here today
and share your experience with us.
Thank you so much.
- Thank you.
(audience applauding)
- Weren't they amazing?
I can't tell you how incredible, again,
I have to emphasize, they worked so hard all week
to get information from us as community college leaders
and say, "Here's a potential problem we have,"
and to work all week.
And then, on the Friday, the fifth day,
after some sleepless nights,
be able to pitch and present, it really showed for us
how we're preparing students to be workforce ready.
We're teaching them not just some of the technical skills,
but those enduring skills, such as teamwork,
critical thinking, problem solving, communication.
It wasn't easy, (alarm ringing)
but they did it.
Next summer, the Digital Center does plan
to partner again with AWS
and Cal Poly Digital Transformation Hub,
so that we can do this again and replicate and scale.
And we wanna partner with all of you.
We supported almost a hundred students this year.
We hope to be able to increase that,
because we found from talking to the students
that the experience was so transformative, so important,
especially for our commuter students
who don't always have that connection,
and a way to come together for a week,
and be immersed in these skills and these ideas.
So stay tuned.
Next year, we'll be sending out information to you,
because we want to know how we can connect more students,
more of your students into this project.
Again, I want to thank you so much.
Thank you to the students.
Thank you to Brian Johnsrud for presenting to us today
and helping us understand and unpack a little bit more
about creativity, and critical thinking, and technology.
And now, I want to introduce the next speaker,
which is Sowmya Kannan from IBM.
(audience applauding) (cheerful music)
- Hello, everyone.
I'm Sowmya Kannan, a pleasure to be here.
I am the Director for Academic Initiatives
and Workforce Development at IBM.
IBM is proud to be a sponsor of this event,
and we strongly believe that the best future is the one
that we all create together.
So great to be here,
and let's see if this does its magic.
All right, so, you know,
I'm preaching to the choir here
when I say technological advances are happening really fast,
and the skills gap is incredible.
And that is what is preventing a rapid pace of innovation
and economic development at the same time.
And we at IBM are here to work
with you to close that gap.
And as Chancellor Christian said,
and she's highlighted this, right, how do we make sure
that the benefits of these technological advancements
reach everyone, right?
And that's a part of the conversation here.
IBM is committed to training,
skilling 30 million people by 2030.
And as a part of this overall commitment,
we aim to train 2 million people in AI by 2026.
IBM SkillsBuild is IBM's education offering.
It is part, it is completely free of cost
for educators and students,
and it helps learners prepare for careers
with job skills courses and credentials.
However, it's not just about online courses.
I was at the booth yesterday and someone asked me,
"Oh, is this another mooc?"
No, it's more than a mooc,
right? (audience chuckling)
IBM SkillsBuild is a comprehensive offering.
It is a package of not just online courses,
but rich learning experiences,
cohort-based learning experiences,
guided learning with support from mentors
who work in industry,
and group innovation challenges,
where students actually are working on hands-on,
going through prescriptive hands-on labs to learn content,
but also, building more expansive capstone like projects.
And they walk out of the learning experience
with a project portfolio,
which they can showcase to their employers.
So it's really critical to build
that well-rounded learning experience
for students, where they are,
it's show, don't tell employers what you can do, right?
Do you have the connections in industry?
Do you have mentors who can guide you
through your career journey?
So those are all the pieces
that we are bringing together in these learning experiences.
AI, so the conversation's all about AI.
And as I talk to faculty and students,
and my role is global,
so I'm talking to folks in California
and the rest of the country here,
as well as students and faculty from Europe, Middle East,
JPAC, and so on.
And why, you know, there's a certain,
one kind of concerns with or opportunity
with computer science students,
but then, there's the rest of us, right,
who are not computer science students,
who are interested in sports, and media, and arts,
and creativity, and language, and communications,
and whatever that may be
for your major of study.
And so, what, with the approach we've taken
with AI learning is,
how does AI apply to an industry
or a career role that you're interested in?
So in the last year, we've come out
with a lot of new content.
For example, I've listed a few courses here,
but it's not a comprehensive list.
For example, AI and healthcare.
What is the application of AI in healthcare,
AI in legal?
What are the ethical considerations
with respect to using AI, with respect to building with AI,
and building AI itself, in terms of models,
and so on, right?
So there are many layers of ethical considerations there,
and we've kind of taken that approach,
a more well-rounded approach with respect to AI education.
In addition to AI, there's also, you know,
all of the core principles and technologies
that we, students, need to learn about
and depending on their career interest, again,
is cyber security, healthcare, cloud,
all of those are domains
that we also address as a part of our content offerings.
And this is, again, not a comprehensive list.
There are courses for web development, design thinking,
communication, and presentation skills.
The previous speaker was talking about
all of those core skills
that you need to be successful at work.
There's been a lot of exciting progress in California.
Last month, we announced a collaboration
with the state of California to bring AI skills
to California Community Colleges.
We also worked
with the Bay Area Community College Consortium
to embed cybersecurity and data analytics certificates
into the curriculum.
Diablo Valley State College is offering academic credit
to their students for this coursework.
And that serves as a really powerful driver
for students to lean into this learning.
I'm particularly excited about our collaboration
with San Jose State University as well.
There, we are working with faculty and students
to train both faculty, as well as students on AI
and to accelerate AI education within their ecosystem there.
One particular highlight is that we work with faculty
and teams of students there,
and students built an AI assistant using watsonx,
IBM watsonx to track and reduce carbon emissions.
So that was a particularly interesting project
with lots of insights for the students
on the application of AI technology.
So join us if you are looking
to bring innovation and learning and helping,
really helping your students meet the moment
that we are in today.
I would encourage you to connect with me on LinkedIn
or my colleagues sitting here
in the third row in the middle here,
Lillian Lei, connect with us on LinkedIn and reach out.
We'd love to work with you.
You can also go directly to skillsbuild.org.
All of the courses are open and completely free.
You can offer them for extra credit
or in some form, get your students exposed
to these learning offerings today.
Pleasure talking to you.
We'll stay in touch, thank you.
(audience applauding)
(cheerful music)
- I know.
Once again, (audience chuckling)
good afternoon, everyone.
We're super excited to, first of all, thank IBM
for their sponsorship of the summit in general,
and in particular, of our closing keynote session.
So we're very excited
about having their support in this endeavor.
So please join me in welcoming Henk Rogers,
a visionary entrepreneur and climate advocate
who has dedicated his career
to transforming how we power our planet.
As the founder of the Blue Planet Foundation
and Blue Planet Energy, Henk has been at the forefront
of renewable energy, innovation,
and climate policy for over two decades.
His groundbreaking work began with successfully lobbying
for Hawaii's historic mandate,
requiring a 100% renewable energy by 2045,
the first such commitment in the United States.
Henk's unique background combines pioneering
experience and technology.
He's perhaps best known
for securing the worldwide rights to Tetris
and creating Japan's first major role playing video game.
With deep expertise in climate solutions
and energy storage systems,
his proven track record includes inspiring 15 other states
and two territories
to adopt similar renewable energy mandates
and founding the Blue Planet Alliance
in 2021 to export the successful model globally
to islands and countries worldwide.
His ambitious 2045 timeline was deliberately chosen
to coincide with the 100th anniversary
of the United Nations, making it a global milestone
for solving the climate crisis.
Today, Henk will share his bold vision, titled,
"We Will Fix Everything by 2045,"
a roadmap for how strategic policy change, renewable energy,
innovation, and global collaboration can accelerate our path
to sustainable future.
Please welcome Henk Rogers.
(audience applauding) (cheerful music)
- Testing, 1, 2, 3.
So I heard I was gonna be giving the closing keynote
at this amazing gathering.
And so, I worked really hard and wrote a speech.
(audience chuckling)
When they first asked me to speak,
they labeled me as a something to do with AI and jobs.
And so, I started thinking about that,
and so, I'll tell a couple of stories
before I get into what I really want to talk about today.
It's 1594, and there's a Dutch farmer.
I'm originally from the Netherlands.
And there's a Dutch farmer, and he invents a sawmill.
And this thing is a, it's a windmill,
and it's got like 16 blades that go up and down.
And it drags the log from the canal
into these 16 blades and cuts,
16 blades cut a log into 17 planks.
That's his idea.
So he goes to the Sawyer's guild in Amsterdam,
and he says, "I got this great,
new labor-saving device invention."
And he demonstrates it to them.
And they said, "There is no effing way we're gonna let
this thing anywhere near anywhere where we work,
because we're all gonna lose our jobs."
Okay?
So he said, "Okay, you don't want it, that's fine."
He goes, and he does it anyway.
He does it, you know, a couple of miles from Amsterdam.
He builds it.
Holland went from being the smallest,
how can I say, maritime country in Europe, to the biggest.
How do they do that?
When they started log, creating those planks,
they improved the efficiency
of creating planks by 3000%.
Instead of doing something that took four months,
it would now take a week.
Holland out planked England and France put together
and became the greatest maritime nation in Europe.
Beat the Spanish in a war on the ocean,
and the same thing, beat the Brits.
So all those people who were sawing planks
before by hand end up building ships.
Now, there's a moral to the story, of course.
I mean, like, you think
that a labor saving device is gonna destroy your job.
No, it's not.
It's gonna create other jobs.
1934 is the other one.
1934, there was a strike,
the long dock worker strike in San Francisco.
Two people died, a couple hundred people were injured.
It was a major, major strike.
And so, it changed labor laws, and so on, and so forth.
But today, how many dock workers do we have?
We have containers, so there's no more dock workers.
So what did all those people do?
They drive trucks, or they have other jobs.
Anyway, AI is like that.
It's coming along and it's going to,
yes, it's gonna take away jobs that are,
in my humble opinion, not really jobs.
You know, if a machine can do what I do,
it's not a job, it's, a machine should do what I do.
That's just the way I think about it.
My name is Henk Rogers.
I majored in computer science
and minored in Dungeons and Dragons
(audience laughing) at the University of Hawaii
in the late seventies.
This is before personal computers.
I moved to Japan, and six years later, in 1983,
when personal computers came out in Japan,
these were not IBMs,
they were like Japanese NECs from Japan's Sharp.
They all made their own computers back then.
I decided I'm gonna write a,
create a computer game.
So is anybody here coding?
Yeah, okay.
I wrote the first role playing game in Japan in 64K.
- [Audience Member] Wow. (audience laughing)
- That includes graphics,
it includes the story, (Henk chuckling)
it includes everything.
Who needs more than 64K, anyway?
(audience laughing)
So it was the number one game in Japan in 1984.
It launched my career as a publisher.
I wrote the first two games for the company.
Then, I traveled around the world looking
for games to bring to Japan.
And at a consumer electronic show in Las Vegas in 1988,
I found a little game called Tetris.
Now, how many of you played Tetris?
(audience muttering)
Oh, I'm so sorry, or... (audience laughing)
I don't know which way that one should go.
But I published Tetris in Japan
on seven different personal computer platforms,
none of which were compatible,
and on the Nintendo family computer,
which is the NES machine in the US.
And that year, Nintendo came out with Gameboy.
(audience exclaiming)
And in 1989, they were going to come out
with Gameboy in the US and the rest of the world.
And Nintendo had a policy
of including a game every time they release a new platform,
because they don't want somebody to buy a machine
and not be able to play a game right away.
And I thought Tetris would be the perfect game
for Gameboy.
And it turns out that it was.
So I went to meet with Mr. Arakawa,
the President of Nintendo of America, and I said,
"Mr. Arakawa,
I think I have the perfect game for Gameboy.
You should include this, you know, Tetris,
you should include it with every Gameboy."
And he said, "Why should I include Tetris?
I have Mario."
(audience chuckling)
And I said, "If you want little boys to buy your Gameboy,
include Mario.
If you want everyone to buy your Gameboy, include Tetris."
And he called in his experts,
he called in his experts, and they agreed.
And so, we made a deal, we shook hands,
and I didn't have the rights for Tetris for Gameboy.
Nobody did.
So in February of 1989,
I got on a plane with the tourist visa
to go to the Soviet Union
to find who had the rights to Tetris, which organization.
If you want to know that story,
there's a movie on Apple TV, have any of you've seen that?
- [Audience Member] Yeah. - There's a movie on Apple-
- [Audience Member] Oh.
- TV called, "Tetris." - [Audience Member] Yeah.
- The guy who played Elton John in "Rocketman" plays me,
or the... (audience laughing)
So his name is Taron Egerton.
He's a up and coming actor.
Very good actor, actually.
He looks nothing like me. (audience laughing)
He looks nothing like me, but he's a great actor.
So it was, you know, and I went through the script,
and it was kind of terrifying,
'cause the script had so much Hollywood nonsense in it.
(audience chuckling)
Car chase?
(audience laughing)
Seriously?
So anyway, I thought,
"Oh, this is gonna be such a man-made movie."
And so, I was,
I just sort of like shivered.
And when I went to watch the movie
for the first time, and it was actually a movie.
I actually cried several times
in that movie about things that never happened.
(audience laughing)
You know, me not showing up for my daughter's performance,
and et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
- [Audience Member] Oh. - All made up stuff.
And if you want to know the truth about
what actually happened back then,
I released a book on April Fool's Day this year.
It was called, "The Perfect Game..."
subtitled, "Tetris: from Russia With Love."
And so, it's my first foray into writing a book.
And actually, if you want to wait for the audio book,
I've just finished doing that too.
I spent four days in the studio reading my own book.
(audience laughing)
So fast forward, it's 2005,
and I just sold a company.
And the company was a company
that makes games for mobile phones.
We had, Tetris is our big game.
And of course, we had the number one game
in mobile phones at that time.
Sold it for a bunch of money.
A month afterwards, I found myself
in the back of an ambulance on the way
to a hospital in Hawaii, living in Hawaii at the time,
with a hundred percent blockage of the widow maker.
- [Audience Member] Oh no. (audience murmuring)
- A hundred percent blockage of the widow maker kills 95%
of the people that that happens to, 95.
So I'm the lucky 5%.
I didn't know that was happening.
They were taking me in for observation,
that they weren't even gonna turn on the siren.
When the siren went on, I knew something hit the fan.
And so, I said at that moment, I said,
"No, I'm not going.
I still have stuff to do." (audience chuckling)
That's what I said.
If I have to hold my breath for 15 minutes,
then, I'm gonna do that.
Whatever it is, they're gonna bring me back.
I have two stents.
That's 20 years ago.
I've had no problem since, so obviously, it all worked.
Oh gosh, modern science, two stents,
I left the hospital four days later with two band-aids.
(audience chuckling)
Anyway, in the recovery room, I started thinking,
what did I mean by "stuff?"
I had already made enough money,
so my wife didn't need me anymore.
(audience laughing)
My kids were already out of college,
so my kids didn't need me anywhere.
So I was kind of done with the kind of stuff
that you normally think that you need to accomplish.
I should retire and play golf, but that's not me.
So anyway, I started thinking,
what is it that's going to upset me
if I didn't do something about it by the end of my life,
by the real end of my life?
And so, I decided to find my missions in life.
And the first mission came to me
in the back of the newspaper.
This is still in the recovery room, it's in Hawaii.
It's the Hawaii newspaper, the back of the newspaper now,
by the obituaries, it's like,
"Oh, by the way, we're going to kill all the coral
in the world by the end of the century."
It was like, "What?
What's causing that?"
"Ocean acidification."
"What's causing that?"
"Carbon dioxide."
"And what's causing that?"
"We are."
So mission number one, end use of carbon-based fuel.
That's where it started.
But once I looked into carbon dioxide, I found out,
oh my gosh, this thing is causing all the climate change.
It's like, it's a disaster.
So anyway, that mission,
end the use of carbon-based fuel,
can sound like a big mission.
It can, but it doesn't have to be.
Just another thing to do.
I started my first foundation,
a first non-profit, called it a foundation,
which is a big mistake,
'cause everyone thinks you're going to give them money.
(audience laughing)
That's not what we do.
We do stuff.
Anyway,
so, and we said about ending the use
of carbon-based fuel in Hawaii.
Now, at the time, Hawaii imported $5 billion,
billion dollars a year of oil
and a billion dollars of coal.
Out of the billion dollars, 30% is jet fuel,
30% is ground transportation,
40%, or $2 billion, is making electricity.
So $2 billion, plus a billion,
$3 billion of fossil fuel was being used
to make electricity every single year.
That's a million and a half people, plus tourists,
plus military.
So that's a lot of money.
And that is kind of reproduced on some similar scale
on every other island in the world.
In fact, it's worse.
We import oil, 'cause we have refineries,
and most islands import diesel, which is already refined,
which means it's more expensive.
So anyway, electricity generation was the biggest use
of fossil fuel sights.
I said, "We're gonna go after that.
If we do that one, then, people will see,
'Hey, we can take on the biggest problem, solve that,
and then, they can go on and solve the smaller problems
to give them the confidence.'"
We tried everything.
I mean, I knew nothing about this when we started.
We tried talking to the governor.
She said, "You know nothing about this."
We had a female,
not saying that that had anything to do with it.
I'm just saying that she said,
"You don't know what you're talking about."
And I didn't.
I said, "I will, I'll learn."
And same thing with the politicians.
And then, the electric company wouldn't give us
the time of day, utility.
And we tried everything.
We ended up deciding that we're gonna get the people
on our side.
And so, how do you get to the people?
How did people in this country stop smoking?
It wasn't because there's a label on the package
that says that this stuff is gonna kill you.
(audience chuckling)
It was because our children asked us to stop.
There was a campaign to get our children
to ask their parents to stop smoking.
So I said, "Okay, the children is the way to go."
So we had children go door to door
and exchange 300,000 light bulbs,
and thereby, having a conversation between a child
and adult about efficiency, about saving money.
Because an an LED light bulb uses one 10th the electricity
of an incandescent light bulb.
So we traded them,
and we made bouquets of incandescent light bulb
and gave them to the politicians.
(audience chuckling) You know, things like that.
Eventually, we prevailed, and we passed a law in Hawaii.
We're the first state in the country
to have a law that says Hawaii has
to go a hundred percent renewable.
We wanted 2040, they were gonna give us 2050.
We negotiated, and we got 2045.
That's where the 2045 date came from.
And my son pointed out to me, you know,
that happens to be the hundredth anniversary
of the United Nations.
So that kind of, yeah, somehow that number came to me.
It came to us, and it means something.
So we followed it up by changing the business model
of the utility, so that they make more money
by switching to renewables.
Now, they paid, at that time,
or still do, maybe more, 25 cents per kilowatt hour for oil,
25 cents per kilowatt hour.
When they put out RFPs, requests for proposal
for renewable energy, wind and solar came in
at about 8 cents per kilowatt hour.
- [Audience Member] Oh!
- And if you add batteries, which you need,
because wind and solar are intermittent,
it's up to 12 cents per kilowatt hour.
That's still less than half of the cost of oil.
So their old business model was two
and a half sales, 10% on the price of oil,
what a dumb ass business model.
Ten percent on the price of oil means they're happy
when the price of oil goes up.
That's two and a half cents.
We said, "Okay, you make 3 cents on the renewables."
Guess who's our best friend now?
(audience chuckling)
So Hawaii today, that was 10 years ago.
Today, Hawaii's at 38% renewable energy.
Some parts are faster, some parts are slower.
And it's not all easy.
You know, we're having problems with the government trying
to bring in LMG at this point,
which is a, it's not a bridge, it's a pier, in my opinion.
So anyway, Hawaii's on track.
Two years later, California copied us.
They credit us for having come up with the legislation,
and they passed the same legislation,
a hundred percent renewable by 2045.
Followed by Illinois, New York, Washington, Oregon.
Fifteen other states now have the same legislation.
So over 50% of the people in this country live
in a state that is gonna go
a hundred percent renewable energy
by 2040,
2045, 2050.
It's a little bit different state by state.
It's working!
It's working.
We're halfway there.
Now, we, of course, focused on the easy half,
but I mean, that's still, you know,
let's focus on the easy half.
Here's the problem.
The problem is that the United States is only 4.3%
of the people in the world.
And so, even if we're a hundred percent renewable energy,
that still leaves 96% of the rest of the world to go.
So we decided, well, I decided that we're gonna have
to do the same thing we did in the US, outside the US.
So we started the Blue Planet Alliance.
I moved to New York,
so I could be close to the United Nations.
And we started doing the same thing we did
in the US, outside.
So how do we do that?
We bring islands, first of all, islands,
because they're the ones who suffer the most
from climate change
and they pay the highest for electricity.
So we bring islands, we bring them to Hawaii,
show them what we did.
Now what we bring them to Hawaii, it's four people,
it's someone from the government, someone from the utility,
someone from the regulatory agency,
and someone from the community,
like, an environmentalist.
No women, no pay.
Meaning, if there's no woman in the mix,
we don't pay for their airfare.
They have to pay their own way.
Our board is always going to be a majority of women.
- [Audience Member] Ah. (Henk chuckling)
- Men got us into this,
and I have absolutely no confidence
that men can get us out of this.
(audience laughing) (audience applauding)
So yes, we have women on our board,
and some of them are very vocal and very strong.
So one woman, no women, no pay.
(audience chuckling)
We have so far brought 35 islands,
Caribbean, sorry, Pacific, Caribbean,
Indian Ocean Islands, to Hawaii, and two countries.
And coming up, we do this every six months,
eight to 10 countries, island countries.
And we keep them for a week,
two days where they get to meet everybody
that was involved in the transition,
the naysayers, the before and after people.
Then, in the middle of the week on Wednesday,
we take them around the island, show them what we've done,
and I mean, all the renewable island,
renewable energy projects.
And then, we spend a couple
of days teaching them how to work together.
Then, on Friday, each team gets to present
what's the solution for their island, you know,
based on listening to us
and what they know about their island.
And then, we send them back.
And then, we have a team of experts,
if you wanna call 'em that,
that have been doing all the presentations.
They basically are there to support them
after they go back.
So they have questions,
whatever, they run into roadblocks.
We're having a roadblock in Bermuda right now.
I was on a Zoom just before this.
And they have the LNG problem.
Somebody wants to bring in LNG.
Okay, so that's the foundation, that's the alliance.
Oh, by the way, I'm a computer game designer.
Did I tell you that already? (audience chuckling)
Yeah, I did.
So whenever I go to a conference, and we're in a room,
and we're trying to figure out how to fix climate change,
somebody comes up with a bright idea, "Let's gamify this."
(audience laughing)
And then, Edward looks at me and said,
"Okay, when are you gonna get to work?"
- [Audience Member] Yeah.
- It's like, "Wait, wait, wait.
I'm not in the game business anymore."
It's hard enough to get somebody to play a game.
And if you try to get somebody to play a game
that has some kind of lesson
that they're supposed to like, learn,
and then, apply in the real world, that's like impossible.
There's too many games out there.
I remember there was an ad,
an ad for a game.
It's like, you play this game,
and you don't have to learn anything.
(audience chuckling)
You don't have to learn anything.
Like, okay, all right.
So that's a hard thing, but anyway,
finally, I gave in.
I said, "Okay, I'm gonna think about this."
And so, I'm making,
pretty soon, it's going into testing.
I made a role playing game for action.
You could say climate action, but it's any kind of action.
Call it the Action App.
And what the Action App does,
it answers the question, you know?
Like, I give a talk like this, and at the end of the talk,
some people come up to me and say, "So what can I do?"
And I say, "I don't know what you can do.
You have to figure out what you can do, and do that."
You know?
Everybody's different.
Figure out what you don't like about the world
and go and fix that.
I mean, you don't have to fix what I want you to fix,
fix what you want you to fix.
And then, I realized
that I really haven't helped them at all.
They're just as puzzled about what they should do next
as they were before they asked me the question.
So the Action App is a list of things to do.
And in the beginning, they're tiny things.
They're pick up a piece of rubbish,
put it in the rubbish cans,
switch the lights, turn off the light switch
in a room where there's no people.
And you do a bunch of those small things,
and then, you go up a level.
That's role playing. (audience chuckling)
Now, you're level two.
And level two means you get to do bigger things.
In Dungeon and Dragons, you get to fight bigger monsters.
But these are bigger things to do.
And you know, maybe the things
in the beginning take a minute, then, they take 10 minutes.
Level three maybe takes an hour, and then, so on.
By the time you're up to level five or six,
you're doing things that take a week.
And what do you get for it?
You get status.
Status, I mean, when you think about it,
everything we do, the money,
and so on, it's all about status.
Bigger car, better television, farther vacation,
bigger lawn, bigger house, bigger this,
bigger that, more expensive, this or that.
And these are all status symbols.
So let's go straight to the status.
And the way I want the status to work is
when Taylor Swift goes to have a concert somewhere,
on Monday, the level sixes get to buy tickets,
on Tuesday, level five, and then, Wednesday level four,
and so on.
The same price, but the people who have done the most
for the environment
or have taken the most action will be sitting in the front.
So you're...
And then, basically, the artist, or the sports team,
or the stadium can take credit for having caused
all those people to take all that action.
So there's two ways that you can make points.
One is you can do the actions,
but two is you can create an action.
When you create an action
and somebody else does it, you get points.
So then, it becomes a big competition
to see who can create the most actionable action.
(audience chuckling)
And I think at the end of the day,
instead of having, you know, like, putting up a silly video,
or a little story, or whatever,
and getting likes, now, we're getting actions.
The AI is watching to see how much of an impact
carbon impact, pollution, whatever it is,
social impact, whatever those impacts are,
the AI is watching and calculating
how many people have done it,
and how much of a difference does it make?
So even if it's a small action,
if a lot of people do it, it makes a big difference.
And I want to, I have this vision, you know,
it's the concert, and the QR code comes up,
and the first action
that everybody's there is,
"Pick up the rubbish that's around you."
And it'll be the cleanest, (audience chuckling)
the cleanest concert ever.
And then, everybody in that concert will realize,
oh my gosh, if we all just pick up after ourselves,
the world will be a better place.
I go to Burning Man,
I just came back from Burning Man a couple of weeks ago,
(audience chuckling)
no matter out of place.
And if there's anything that I learned at Burning Man
that I want to bring to the rest of the world,
it's no matter out of place.
So actually, I have a lot of time left.
Anybody want me to talk about something else?
(Henk chuckling) (audience laughing)
So I started thinking of, you know,
so what does it all mean?
You know,
when do we fix climate change?
When do we fix plastic in the ocean?
When do we fix anything?
And the answer is that
if we don't have a deadline,
nothing happens.
No building has ever been built
that didn't have a deadline
that said you have to have this building built
by such and such a date.
I'm going to go to the moon by the end of this decade.
That's a deadline.
If that deadline didn't exist,
we would still be thinking about
how we're gonna go to the moon, but we went,
because we had a deadline.
So fixing climate change,
just like anything else, needs a deadline.
Everything needs a deadline that we have to get done.
And that's the one thing that I feel that is missing.
You know, the target for the IPCC is we wanna stay
below 1.5 degrees warming.
What does that mean to anybody?
First of all, there's Celsius, then, Fahrenheit,
they're different.
So 1.5 degrees Celsius,
nobody in America understands what that is.
1.5 degrees warmer, what's wrong with that?
I don't have to wear a jacket.
You know, they don't understand that difference.
And then, if there's no way for us to measure that
as individuals, as people, we rely on scientists.
And there's a lot of people that are out there
that basically don't believe science,
or they think science is a belief system.
It's funny, because they fly on planes.
(audience laughing) (Henk chuckling)
You know?
And it's like, "Yeah, yeah, I fly on a plane."
Well, that's science!
Without science and engineering, that plane would not fly.
It wouldn't even exist.
So I mean, like, it's not a belief system.
It's different from a belief system.
Anyway, so
the point is that we just need to make a decision.
Now, if we go back in time,
and people don't like when I tell this story,
but I'm gonna tell it anyway.
It's World War II, the beginning of World War II.
We went from, in five years, we went from biplanes
to jet planes.
We invented missiles, cruise missiles,
sonar, radar, the atom bomb.
This is in five years using 1940s technology,
five years.
This is 2025.
There ain't nothing we can't do today.
And with AI, are you kidding me?
We have at least a 3000% increase in productivity.
Back to that productivity thing.
There's, AI's gonna help us.
We're not going to forget anything anymore.
You know, like, people have invented things in history.
You know, what did Nikola Tesla invent?
You know, he died,
and a lot of his stuff was like lost in history.
What was he building in New Jersey?
And these things are all kind of lost.
But today, all that information will never be lost again.
And AI will help us sift through
and figure out what's the better of those technologies,
and we'll get them done.
All we need to do is decide
by when we want to fix climate change,
by when we want to fix plastic in the ocean,
by when we want to clean up our rivers,
by when we want to cure some disease,
all of this can be done.
We just have to have a deadline.
I have four missions.
I have four kids,
so I decided I was gonna have four missions.
(audience chuckling)
And somewhere in the back of my mind, I was thinking
that each of my kids were gonna pick up one of my missions.
(audience chuckling)
That is so not happening. (audience laughing)
That is so not happening.
So my second mission is to end war.
And I'm back a generation, when it was 19, gosh,
1971 I think, Kent State happened.
And we went demonstrating,
"1, 2, 3, 4, we don't want your blank in war."
They told me I can't use dirty words.
(audience chuckling)
And so, my mission back then was to end war.
I mean, this is ridiculous.
Why did we go to Vietnam and kill people
and die, for what?
At some point, the young people
of the world are gonna say, "You know what?
You want to fight a war?
You go fight it."
Say it to the old people,
'cause it's old people that decide to go to war,
it's not young people.
Old people decide, "Hey, you have to go to war.
You have to go to war,
and don't come back until you've killed somebody."
What about the first, I mean, the 10 Commandments,
the first commandment, "Thou shall not kill."
How does that jive?
It doesn't say except if it's for your country.
(audience chuckling)
It's just, "Thou shall not kill," period.
I lived in Japan for 18 years,
and it used to be lots of little countries,
and they killed each other, you know, for territory,
for minerals, for God knows what.
And they found out, hey, there were other people out there
that had bigger guns.
And all of a sudden, they realized, "Hey, you know what?
We're not all these little countries,
we're actually all Japanese."
And that's what has to happen to the world.
The whole world has to realize
that we're not lots of little countries.
We're all one people.
Anyway, that's war.
I'd like there to be a date in the future
that says from that date on,
there will no longer be any war heroes, only war criminals.
If you kill somebody, you're a murderer, period.
We need to switch that thinking.
There is no reason
why you should ever kill anybody for anything.
Mission number three is to make a backup of life
by going to other planets.
And my friend Rolf is here.
He does things with NASA as well.
I have a little test facility
where we test living on Mars or the moon.
I think that the natural progression
for human beings is to go off planet.
We have explored every place on this planet,
and there's this energy that's within us
that wants us to explore more.
And the more we explore in this planet,
the more damage we do.
So it really is time for us to move on.
And nature, when you think about it,
you have all of life on earth,
is, as far as we know, this is the only place
that has life as we know it.
I mean, we've looked, and I've hung out with a woman
that does the surfer extraterrestrial intel in SETI.
We haven't heard anything in, what,
40, 50 years, something like that.
Why is that?
There's a lot of different reasons.
The equation, the Drake equation says
that there should be tons and tons
of civilizations out there,
but we haven't heard from anyone.
And it could be that civilizations don't last very long.
Like, we could be headed to the end of this civilization,
and then, we'd stop broadcasting.
So the period of broadcasting only lasts a couple
of hundred years.
And in the scope of things, like the billions of years,
if civilizations only broadcast for like 200 years,
we might miss that.
And that's the reason we might not hear somebody
from somewhere else.
But be that as it may, life
has propagated to every possible ecosystem in the world.
I mean, ever.
The coldest, the hottest,
the most inhospitable place, life is there.
Why is that?
It's just for survival.
In case things change, and things have changed in the past.
We've had mass extinctions on this planet,
where 90 something percent of the species died,
but that last 4%, 4, 5% repopulated the entire planet.
And that is nice if you have a planet to repopulate.
But there is, you know,
it's possible we could get hit by a big rock from space.
We could have a supernova event in the neighborhood,
which would like, fry us.
And eventually, the sun is going to nova itself.
So we need to make it back up.
And that's the whole, that mission number three.
At this point in time, I pretty much disagree with Elon
about everything, except for that.
I still agree with him on that.
And he wants to go, and I want to make sure
that when we get there, we do the right thing.
We treat the place, wherever we go, with respect.
And we don't trash the place like we've trashed this planet.
Mission number four, you're gonna love this one.
Find out how the universe ends and do something about it.
(audience chuckling)
Now, why do I have that mission?
And I think I have that mission, because it's a big mission.
I was at a TED conference and somebody gave a talk,
and they said, "You know, if you can complete your missions
in your lifetime, your missions aren't big enough."
So here is one mission that isn't gonna be completed
in my lifetime, for sure.
And it makes the other ones seem small.
And in the scope of things, like the Industrial Revolution,
or the invention of the wheel, all those things happened.
And they, in the scope of things, they're small.
Ending climate change is small.
It's not huge.
It's just a thing that we have to do.
Now, all we have to do to solve climate change is
to set that deadline.
I'd like that deadline to be 2045.
I mean, it could be any time.
I'm giving them, the electric companies,
lots of time to make the change.
That's still 20 years.
20 years, are you kidding me?
This is not World War, maybe it is.
Maybe it is,
maybe it is another World War, and we have to survive it.
But in 20 years, we can definitely do this.
All we need to do is have a deadline and determination.
People ask me if I have hope.
I say, "No, I do not have hope.
I have determination, because we're gonna do this.
This is all of us, and you are now part of the team."
I'm gonna say to you, if you're an old engineer,
if there are any engineers in here,
you guys got us into this.
(audience chuckling)
You guys gotta get us out.
We can't just give it to our kids.
This is the big problem.
And the quicker we solve the problem,
the less damage we do.
So please join me in ending climate change by 2045.
Name of the organization is the Blue Planet Alliance.
It means alliance of everybody.
So here we go.
Thank you.
(audience applauding)
- One more hand for Henk Rogers.
All right, we are in the home stretch.
You are the faithful, so thank you for sticking with us.
What an amazing few days we've had together.
And I want to begin by thanking everyone on the team
who made the Future Summit
and the related events possible this week.
We know we've created a lot
of different experiences for you,
and we definitely are looking forward to your feedback
as we plan next year's summit.
Also, we have one more to go tomorrow.
So for folks who are interested
in faculty professional development,
if you don't know about that
and you are interested in participating,
just reach out to one of the team members,
and we'll connect you with that.
Also, just wanted to call out the Chancellor's office staff,
the Foothill-De Anza Community College District Team,
our new founding partners, our AI fellows,
our change makers.
You can clap for yourselves as you're in the audience.
(audience cheering) (audience applauding)
Our ambassadors and scholars, the foundation
for California Community College's events team,
our summit sponsors, all of the industry
and philanthropic partners.
And again, we could not do this without you.
If I forgot anyone, I apologize.
This is why I'm not using names,
(presenter chuckling) (audience chuckling)
because you always forget somebody.
Again, the the planning team was just blown away this year.
We had over 700 registered for the summit,
which was up from 400 last year,
so thank you for being here.
Thank you for spreading the word,
and just when our collective team thought that it was safe
to sit back and relax, we're already scoping out
what next year's summit will look like in next September.
So save a little date on your calendar.
We'll push those specific dates out soon
and would definitely look forward to having you back.
As we come to the close of the summit,
I want to pause and reflect on where we began,
what we've explored together, and where we go from here.
On the first day, Chancellor Christian set the tone
with a powerful call to meet the moment
as California's Community College is 116 colleges strong,
over 88,000 faculty, staff,
and administrators serving our 2.2 million students
and to step forward to shape the future of AI.
She shared that special message we had from the governor,
who reiterated his vision,
that our community colleges are core
to training the workforce as the global epicenter
of technology in California,
And that what we not only help improve individual lives,
but also, support a well-rounded citizenry in our state
and our communities.
Our State Chancellor also set out
some clear priorities for us.
The importance of student
and faculty-centered professional development,
the centrality of supporting innovation with infrastructure,
the responsibility to prepare students
for a changing workforce,
and the charge to strive for AI literacy
for all Californians.
So throughout this year's Future Summit
and all the adjacent events that were around it,
we are building out that vision together.
For the past week, our staff, our students,
faculty and administrators made the time to gather together,
despite all of your impossibly busy schedules,
to share your experiences and your expertise
with one another.
Thank you for your creativity, your curiosity,
and your commitment that transforms Vision 2030
from just an aspiration into reality.
So please give yourselves a round of applause.
(audience applauding)
With that, we are definitely looking forward
to seeing you at other events this year
and certainly back here in Silicon Valley next year
for Future Summit 2026.
Thank you for being with us today, and we appreciate you.
Have a great afternoon
and a safe trip home. (participant cheering)
(all applauding)
(upbeat rock music)
♪ Hey, hey, hey, hey ♪